Guide to the Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, Samuel Black McCormick, Administrative Files, 1904-1920 UA.2.10.1904-1920
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, Samuel Black McCormick, Administrative Files
1900-1920
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Chancellor
UA.2.10.1904-1920
2.56 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
This collection contains administrative as wekk as some personal papers of Chancellor Samuel Black McCormick, 1904-1920.
Separated Material
Photographs from McCormick's 1914 trip (folder 28) are located in his papers, RG 90.F8.
Biography
Samuel Black McCormick accepted the position of Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh on June 16, 1904, and was inaugurated on February 22, 1905. He was born in Irwin, Westmoreland County, Pennsylvania, on May 6, 1858 to James Irwin McCormick and Rachel Long Black. A graduate of Washington and Jefferson College, he was admitted to the bar of Allegheny County in 1882. For several years he practiced law but then took Minister's Training at the Western Theological Seminary, graduating in 1890. He accepted a position at the First Presbyterian Church of Omaha, Nebraska, and later became president of Coe College, Iowa.
His most notable achievements were in acquiring the Dental College, the West Penn Medical College and establishing the Schools of Economics (later Business) and Education. In 1909, he moved the campus of the University from Observatory Hill on the Northside to Oakland, and changed its name from Western University of Pennsylvania to the University of Pittsburgh. He presided as Chancellor during the First World War when he and 524 other college presidents were told that the U.S. government was taking over their institutions for the training of officers and technical specialists in the Student Army Training Corps. Shortly after the close of WWI, the 1918 Influenza pandemic descended on cities throughout the U.S.
McCormick resigned as Chancellor in 1920, but continued to have an office in State Hall. He died on April 18, 1928 from pneumonia.
Scope and Content Notes
These are the administrative and some personal papers of Chancellor McCormick, 1904-1920.
Previous Citation
Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, Samuel Black McCormick, Administrative Files, 1904-1920, UA.2.10.1904-1920, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Records and correspondence; Universities and colleges -- Administration -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Correspondence; Administrative records; University of Pittsburgh; McCormick, Samuel Black -- Records and correspondence; University of Pittsburgh -- Administration; University of Pittsburgh. Chancellor -- Records and correspondence
- Programs and writings (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Content Notes
  Commencement Programs: Dr. McCormick was a speaker for Parnassus High School, Hiram College, Shady Side Academy, Pittsburgh and Allegheny Kindergarten College and one other; Some correspondence and biography
- Correspondence, 1900-1904 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Leaving of Coe College; First annual report to the Board of Trustees as Acting Chancellor; Called by Trustees to be Chancellor
- Correspondence, 1904-1905 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Program from Inauguration 1905 and other material; An Act making an appropriation to the Western University of Pennsylvania ($500,000); Committee on new site; Letter to John D. Rockefeller for aid; Brief statement concerning the University
- Correspondence, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Record of dinner given at Hotel Schenley October 30, 1906 by the Trustees; Research on "Strength of tubes" by Reid T. Stewart; Gift of Andrew Carnegie (1906)
- Correspondence, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Merchants & Manufacturers Association; Chamber of Commerce of Pittsburgh; To Mr. A.W. Mellon; Mr. Nicola's proposal on buildings and land for the university; Report of Chancellor to Board of Trustees, June 3, 1907; Proposal of committee on Memorial for the Pittsburgh Female College Association
- Correspondence, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  New Mining building; Acquiring the Medical School; Memo concerning the competition for building plans; Sesquicentennial material, programs, etc.; Statistics; George Lauder letter
- Correspondence, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  General business, Alumni, Funding
- Correspondence, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Psychology Department vacancy
- Correspondence, 1904-1914 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Athletic Department
- Correspondence, 1906-1908 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Campaign for funding
- Correspondence, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Building Program
- Correspondence, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Building Program Architect
- Correspondence, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Perrysville Avenue property sale
- Correspondence, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Westinghouse letter
- Correspondence, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  General correspondence and William A. Robinson case
- Correspondence, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  United Boys Brigade, Union Theological Seminary, University Extension Society, Union Rescue Mission, Ullman and the Classics Dept., University Club
- Correspondence, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Correspondence V-Z: Includes, YMCA and letters from Yocum
- Correspondence, 1910-1912 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Memos from Department Heads for Chancellor's meeting in Harrisburg; University history; School of Education; Black students refused in University Band; Smoke nuisance; Gifts from Trustees; Trees Gymnasium, the first building given in whole by one individual
- Correspondence, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Letters from Henry Buhl about Smith cabinet
- Correspondence, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Letters from Francis Newton Thorpe about European Universities
- Chancellor's Report, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  Includes reports of departments
- Correspondence, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  Law School; Board of Trustees; Facts concerning the University; Distribution of students; An Act – concerning appropriations; List of faculty
- Registrar's Report, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- 125th Anniversary, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  Notes on the celebration of the 125th Anniversary of the founding of the Pittsburgh Academy, February 27-19, 1912.
- 125th Anniversary, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  Programs, Proclamations, Exercises; "The Vision of she-who-knows," by George Seiber (pageant); Official prospectus; Committee on honorary degrees
- Correspondence, 1913-1914 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  Chancellor's report for 1913/14; Gifts list, beginning with 1905-1914; Notes from Deans' reports; Historical address at Erie, PA, by Francis Newton Thorpe "Building of the Fleet"; Salary by academic units; Information bulletins 1914 & 1915; Letter of protest against the 1914 Owl co-ed article.
- Peace Movement, 1913-1915 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  Emergency Peace Federation, World Peace Foundation, St. Louis Peace Conference (1913), Price of peace; World Court Congress; American League to limit armaments; Church Peace Union; Suggested basis upon which to form an international court of arbitration with a view to ending the present conflict in Europe, and to prevent in future all such similar conflicts, by H. Francis Dyruff; Plan for an international court
- McCormick's trip to Europe and the Middle East, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  Handwritten notes of his trip. Includes England, Germany, Switzerland, Italy as well as Greece, Constantinople and Palestine. Some articles written for the Pitt News.
- Correspondence, Governor Martin Brumbaugh, 1914-1915 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  Correspondence with Martin G. Brumbaugh, Governor or Pennsylvania. Invitations, Public Service Commission, various letters of recommendation for appointments.
- Correspondence and other materials on the War in Europe, 1914-1921 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  1914-21 War material; McCormick and others stranded abroad; University's War Activities and Efforts, American soldiers at school; List of addresses delivered outside the university, 1915-17
- Correspondence and minutes, 1915-1918 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  Roswell H. Johnson on Socialism, Bolshevism, Eugenics and Birth Control controversy, 1916-1918; Commencement 1915, Dean's minutes for Feb. 17 and March 3, 1915 and March 31 1920.
- Correspondence and proclamations, 1916-1917 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  Correspondence with PA. Governor Martin H. G. Brumbaugh; Arbor Day proclamations; letter recommending Robert Vann to the Negro National Education Congress, Governor's Thanksgiving proclamation 1915-1918; Agricultural tour; Mansfield's endorsement for PA Board of Motion Picture Censors; Pharmacy and Dental Examiners Boards; Appropriations; League to Enforce Peace; International Industrial Exhibition; Topographic and Geologic Survey Commission; Student's Army Training Corps; Lew H. Palmer
- State Appropriations, correspondence, documents and clippings, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  Correspondence with Babcock and others about state appropriations request; clippings and documents regarding Penn State and Penn's requests; Correspondence with Edgar Fahs Smith and Edwin E. Sparks on appropriations.
- National Education Association, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  Convention in Pittsburgh, 1918. Map of Pittsburgh & Schenley Farms District (good)inside brochure; Tentative draft of a bill to create a Department of Education (U.S.); Program of convention
- State Appropriation correspondence and documents, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Correspondence, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  Chancellor's biography & family ties; Dr. Marley (Miss Auleene) working among islanders (Alumna); Correspondence (personal) between Chancellor S.B. McCormick and his cousin, Lizzie F. McCormick, The Manse, Moneymore, Ireland; January 1918-August 1919
- Correspondence with Andrew Carnegie, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  Also the Carnegie Foundation
- Correspondence with H.J. Heinz, 1916-1920 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  Budget for religious education; Resolution on the death of Henry John Heinz by University Trustees; Heinz House for Christian Associations
- Students in Military Service, 1917-1919 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  Letters of recommendation and related correspondence 1917-1919
- Reserve Officer Training Corps (Box 5, Folder 40)
  Inspection report 9/25/1919; History and evaluation of ROTC program at the university, February 1919; establishment of the program 3/7/1918 and 6/30/1918; List of faculty and students to report to Plattsburg, NY, 7/16/1918; Inspection report; appointment of Lt. Col. Stickle as professor of Military Science 1/1918 correspondence concerning faculty for ROTC; equipment orders; Procedure preliminary to inauguration of Military Training 1916; correspondence related to establishing ROTC program.
- Correspondence, 1918-1920 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  Letter McCormick to T.H. McKnight concerning Medical School; University activities in War (WWI); Lists of Professors and instructors of draft age; College faculty working with Student Army Training Corps 9/9/1918; staff for War Aims course; Lists of essential teachers; Report: "Civil Administration of University of Pittsburgh as a Students' Army Training Corps unit 1919; Letter concerning H.J. Heinz bequest 10/14/1919; agreement with Elizabeth Steel Magee Hospital 5/12/1919 and related correspondence.
- Minutes of Faculty Meetings, 1906-1908 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  Library rules; athletic reports; arrangements for lighting; etc
- Minutes of Faculty Meetings and Special Committees, 1906-1910 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  Medical department; football scholarships; curriculum; literary society, proposed course in engineering
- Minutes of the Finance Committee, 1906-1911 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  Correspondence from A.W. Mellon about stock; expenses; other bonds and stocks; budget matters